（かをり）ニャア！
Ueno Dentist
This way
Sumiya Park Administration Office
Meow!
60th Anniversary Piano Competition
Maihou Newspaper Company, Inc.
[TEL]（♪♪『光るなら』）
Music Room
Sumiya       Junior        High
Crushed it!
（椿）いったー！
She hit it dead on!
芯　食った～！
（部員）すごい　飛球！
Look at it go!
Crash
Crap.
ヤバ…。
（部員）バカみたいに飛ばすなよ！
You don't have to whack the snot out of it!
Go get the ball, Tsubaki!
（部員）ボール　取ってこいよ　椿！
（渡）ま～た　やったのか　あいつ。
She's done it again.
Keep
hands
clear
Pouring water
into the stream
is prohibited.
(Structure may be
moved elsewhere)
（椿）あっ　バイバーイ！
（生徒）バイバーイ！
Bye-bye!
うわー！　死体だー！
A corpse!
*Twitch*
Swipe
Better make a run for it...
（椿）早いとこ　逃げとこ…。
（公生）う～ん。
うん？
（公生）い…　痛…。
Ow...
Oh, Kousei, it's just you.
Thank goodness it wasn't somebody else.
（椿）な～んだ　公生か。
他の人じゃなくて　よかった。
（公生）あれ？　椿　いつ　ここに？
Tsubaki? When did you get here?
（公生）えっ！？　ガラス　割れてる！
視界が　赤い！
Huh?! The window's broken!
I'm seeing red!
You broke another one? We just got that one fixed!
またかよ！　ここの窓
やっと直してもらえたんだぞ。
割ったガラスの数は
強打者の勲章よ。
A slugger's only as good as the
number of windows she's broken.
飛ばし過ぎ。　加減しろ。
You're blasting them too hard! Ease up a little!
手なんか　抜けるかー！
Like hell I'd ever bat with
anything less than my A-swing!
S
n
a
p
S
n
a
p
S
n
a
p
Snap
中学最後の夏だからね。
私は　三冠王になるの！
It's my last summer in middle school, okay?
The Triple Crown is mine for the taking!
取りあえず　ガラス　片さなきゃ。
[TEL]（♪♪『光るなら』）
Whatever. Gotta get this cleaned up.
聞けよ！
Don't ignore me!
Dustpan... Dustpan...
（椿）ちり取り　ちり取りと…。
So I'm gonna have to apologize again?
また　僕が謝るのか…。
And write up the damage report...
あと　破損届も。
危ないじゃない　もう。
Don't be so reckless!
指　ケガしたら　どうすんのよ！
What if you sliced a finger open?
So what if I did?
別に　いいのに…。
Ready
Next-door neighbors, childhood friends...
（渡）家が隣同士　幼なじみ同士→
Where one goes, the other is sure to follow.
所構わず　求め合うねえ。
おしどり夫婦。
[TEL]（シャッター音）
Right, darling hubby and wife?
We are not hubby and wife!
（公生・椿）夫婦じゃねーっ！
Besides, what's up with the cell phone?
（椿）てか　渡
何で　携帯　持ってんのよ。→
部活中でしょ？　サッカー部。
Aren't you in the middle of soccer practice?
土足で入るな　渡。
Don't you dare track your shoes in here, Watari!
（椿）あの　ハゲ教頭め。
That stupid bald vice principal.
Telling us off for an hour over a little broken glass?
ガラス　割ったくらいで
１時間　説教かよ。
１時間だけで済んで
むしろ　よかったじゃん。
Well, at least it was only an hour, right?
１時間　付き合わされた
僕の身にも　なってほしいな。
Put yourself in my shoes. I'm the one
who was stuck with her for that hour.
（椿）だいたいさ
ボールが飛んでく方向に→
Well, they shouldn't have put the school
where the ball could hit it in the first place!
校舎が立ってるのが　おかしいのよ絶対。　そう思うでしょ？
Am I right?
（渡）俺は　いいけどね。→
If it means the ladies can cheer me on
from the windows, it's no skin off my nose.
窓から　女の子が
応援してくれたりするしさ。
Sumiya Junior High
Go figure.
（椿）あー　はいはい。
（渡）あー　腹減ったなー。
Sumiya Junior High
Man, I'm starving.
（椿）色気の次は　食い気かよ。
Sumiya Junior High
From girls to food in the blink of an eye.
（渡）コンビニ　寄ってくけど
どう？
I'm gonna stop by the convenience store. Coming?
付き合う。
（椿）私も～。
Yeah, sure.
I'm in.
第一　おかしいだろ。
何で　僕まで説教されなきゃ…。
I mean, how messed up is that?
Why should I have to get yelled at too?
（椿）うおっ　このアイス　うまっ！
買いだめだ。
This ice cream is delish! Time to stock up!
聞いてない。
She's not even listening.
（渡）しっかし
公生も災難だよな。→
Damn, Kousei. Talk about collateral damage.
On top of getting lectured,
you've gotta write two letters of apology?
説教された上に
反省文　２枚だって？
Oh, it's no sweat. Nothing I can't handle.
こんなの　へっちゃら。
軽いもんさ。
I've been babysitting her since birth,
so it's second nature to me now.
生まれたときから
子守してきたから→
慣れちゃったよ。
Busting a suspension bridge during a field trip,
遠足で　つり橋　壊すわ→
pushing me off a ten-meter diving board...
１０ｍの　飛び込み台から
落とされるわ。
（渡）ハハハ…　小３のときだっけ？
What was that, third grade?
死ぬかと思った。
I thought I was a goner.
（渡・公生）ハハハ…。
（椿）うるさい！
Shut up!
僕　一人っ子なのに
世話の焼ける姉貴がいるみたい。
I may be an only child, but it still feels like
I've got a high-maintenance big sister.
（渡）優しいな　公生は。
You really are a nice guy, aren't you?
You're kidding, right?
（椿）どこがよ？
But you'd better not be too nice, Kousei.
（渡）でも　公生
ほどほどにしとけよ。
You know what they say:
Nice guys are doomed to finish last.
優しいやつは　損するって
決まってんだ。
おおっ！
圭子ちゃんからメール！→
Sweet! I got a text from Keiko!
I've got somewhere to be, guys!
俺　用事できた！　ひゃっほーい！
How many does that make?
何人目？
３人目。
She's number three.
あんなのの　どこが　いいんだか。
Seriously, what do they all see in him?
He's like Mr. Shallow!
ザ　軽薄。
でも　渡は　いいやつだよ。
But you know he's really a good guy.
女の敵だよ。
Women should avoid him like the plague.
What about you, Kousei?
（椿）公生は？
ん？
Huh?
（椿）好きな子　いないの？
えっ？
Isn't there anyone you like?
What?
美和が言ってたよ。
I was talking to Miwa the other day.
She said the world looks more
colorful when you're in love.
好きな人がいると
全部が　カラフルに見えるって。
僕を好きになる人なんか…
いないよ。
No one's gonna bother falling in love with me.
IRKED
（椿）暗い！
Too dark!
Where's the sparkle in your eyes?!
目が光ってない！
私たち　１４歳なのよ！
We're only fourteen, you know!
They don't sparkle 'cause they're
a really deep shade, obviously.
目は黒いから　光らないだろ。
（椿）出た！　常識論。
Oh, you get the point!
Think outside the box for a change!
何となく分かるでしょ？
輝いてないの！
There's no sparkle! You're a teenager,
so they should be all lit up!
思春期なんだから　ピカーっと！
Lit up!
ピカー！
ピカーっと！
Yeah.
Your eyes are lit up, Tsubaki.
椿の目は　輝いている。
《椿の目には→
I'll bet everything looks colorful through her eyes.
きっと　風景が
カラフルに　見えてるんだろうな》
《僕とは違う…》
Unlike mine.
When's your dad coming home?
（椿）お父さん　いつごろ
帰ってくるの？
うーん　１カ月か　２カ月か…。
In a month, maybe two.
（椿）まだ　分かんないんだ。
So you don't know yet.
Well, it varies based on what his company needs.
仕事先の都合で　変わるからね。
（椿）だよね。
Fair enough.
何かあるときは
椿んちに　お願いしてるし→
If anything happens, your family's there to help out.
１人も慣れちゃったしね。
And I've gotten used to being on my own.
じゃ　また　あした。
Well, see you tomorrow.
（椿）うん　また。
Yeah, see you.
Hello?
いや～　ごめん。
今日　言おうと思って忘れてた。→
Oh, my bad!
I was gonna ask him today, but I totally blanked!
うん　あしたには　必ず。→
Yeah!
I'll do it tomorrow for sure.
大丈夫だよ。　私が頼めば。→
Hey, no worries.
If I ask him to...
Yep, it's a sure thing.
うん。　絶対。→
So don't worry, okay?
だから　安心して。
ただいま　母さん。
I'm home...
Mother.
Happily, Cheerily, and Brightly
（椿）《美和が言ってたよ》→
I was talking to Miwa the other day.
《「彼と出会った瞬間
私の人生が変わったの」》→
"The moment I met him,
my life changed.
《「見るもの　聞くもの
感じるもの」》→
Everything I saw, everything I heard,
everything I felt...
《「私の風景　全部が
色づき始めたの」って》
The world around me was suddenly saturated in color".
《でも…　僕には…》
But...
To me...
Everything out there is monotone.
《僕には　モノトーンに見える》
《譜面のように
鍵盤のように…》
Just like a music score.
Just like a keyboard.
From the autumn when I was eleven...
＜１１歳の秋　僕は…→
I...
Your Lie in April
ピアノが弾けなくなった＞
could no longer play the piano.
Your Lie in April
[TEL]（♪♪『光るなら』）
Too easy!
（椿）隙ありーっ！
ぎゃー！
Smack
Man, what a boring reaction.
も～　つまんない反応。
あんたの青春って何？
Doesn't your youth mean anything to you?
１４の春は　二度と来ないのよ！
We'll never have our fourteenth
spring again, you know!
放課後に　１人　教室で…
よいしょ。
Sitting alone in a classroom after school...
何　聴いてんのよ。
What are you listening to?
Don't just yank on those.
あんま　引っ張るなよ。
うひゃー！　あれ？
Hey, isn't this Goose House's new song?!
Ｇｏｏｓｅ　ｈｏｕｓｅの新曲！？
今　ＣＭで流れてるやつ？
The one that plays in that commercial?!
うお～！
《うるさいなぁ》
Oh, cool it already...
[TEL]（♪♪『光るなら』）
（椿）公生　あしたの土曜日
暇でしょ？
Kousei, you're free on Saturday, right?
決め付けるなよ。
Don't just jump to conclusions!
じゃあ　予定あるの？
Oh, so you have plans?
同じクラスの女の子にね→
This girl in my class asked me
to introduce her to Watari,
渡を紹介してほしいって
頼まれてさ。
so we're gonna meet up tomorrow.
あした　会うことになってるの。
公生も来てよ。
You should tag along, Kousei.
Huh? Why do I have to go?
えー？　何で僕も？
私と　その子と渡の３人じゃ
私　気まずいじゃん。
Well, if I'm just a third wheel,
it's gonna be awkward for me.
'Cause you just know it's
gonna get all kinds of romantic.
どうせ　甘い空気になるんだから
２対２なら　ちょうどいい。
But two-on-two would be perfect.
And besides...
それに…。
It turns out she plays classical music.
その子
クラシック　やってるんだって。
You play the piano, so you two'll
have something in common.
公生は　ピアノやってるんだから→
共通の話題があった方が
いいじゃん。
If there's a lull in conversation,
you could talk about instruments and stuff.
話が詰まったときにさ
楽器の話とか　できるでしょ？
But I...
僕は…　ピアノは辞めたんだ。
[TEL]（♪♪『光るなら』）
I gave up playing piano.
I haven't played in two years.
もう　２年も弾いてない。
Liar! You were playing yesterday in the music room!
嘘つき！　昨日　弾いてたじゃん。
音楽室で。
That was for work!
あれは　バイト！
バイト？
Work?
新譜を耳コピして
譜面に起こしてるんだ。
I'm transcribing new songs by ear.
For karaoke and stuff.
カラオケ用とか。
[TEL]（♪♪『光るなら』）
Why bother with the piano
if you can just do it in a classroom?
教室で　できるなら
ピアノ弾く必要　ないじゃん。
音の確認　してただけ。
I was just checking it for accuracy.
ふ～ん。
バイトなんて
他に　いくらでも　あるじゃない。
There are tons of other part-time
jobs out there, you know.
私には…　必死に
しがみついているように見えるよ。
To me...
It sounds like you're still not ready to let it go.
ピアノ弾いてる公生の方が
カッコよかったな。
You were way cooler when you played piano, Kousei.
It was my mother's dream
＜母の夢だった＞
to raise me into a world-class pianist.
＜世界を飛び回るピアニストに
僕を育てること＞
My mother ran a music school.
＜音楽教室を営んでいた
母のレッスンは→
毎日　毎日　何時間も→
I took lessons from her
day after day, for hours on end.
たたかれながら
怒鳴られながら…＞
She would hit me, scold me...
＜泣いても
許してはくれなかった＞
She wouldn't let me off even if I cried.
（早希）《あなたは　私の代わりに
ヨーロッパで活躍するの》
You'll assume my rightful place
as a renowned pianist in Europe.
If it'll make you happy, Mother...
（公生）
《母さんが喜んでくれるなら→
If it'll make you better...
元気になってくれるなら→
僕…　頑張るよ》
I'll do my best.
＜いよいよ　ヨーロッパのコンクールを
視野に入れた３年前→
Three years ago, just when I finally had a European competition in my sights,
母が死んだ＞
my mother passed away.
＜ピアノは嫌いだ＞
I hate the piano.
＜それでも
しがみついているのは→
But if I still can't let it go,
きっと　僕には何もないから＞
it's only because I have nothing else.
＜ピアノを除けば
僕は　空っぽで→
Take away the piano, and I'm empty.
不細工な余韻しか　残らない＞
There's nothing left but an ugly resonance.
（椿）《今日も　聞こえないか…》
I can't hear it today, either...
《遅い。
５分前行動が　なってない》
They're late.
They were supposed to be here five minutes ago.
This was their idea in the first place.
《誘っておいて。　うん？》
To mark the spot?
目印？　魔よけ？
To ward off evil spirits?
女物…だよな。
These are women's, right?
Huh? What's this?
ん？　何だ？
スッ　スパッツ！　えっ！　えー！？
L-Leggings?! What the heck?!
A melodica?
結構　うまい。
Pretty good playing, too.
（椿）《美和が言ってたよ》→
I was talking to Miwa the other day.
"The moment I met him,
《「彼と出会った瞬間
私の人生が変わったの」》→
my life changed.
Everything I saw, everything I heard,
《「見るもの　聞くもの
感じるもの」》→
everything I felt...
《「私の風景　全部が
カラフルに　色づき始めたの」》→
The world around me was suddenly saturated in color,
as if everything had just started to sparkle".
《「世界が　輝きだしたの」》
《涙…》
Tears...
ケホッ　ケホッ…
強く　吹き過ぎちゃった。
I blew into it too hard...
お姉ちゃ～ん！
ん？
Hey, Miss!
ハト　来ないよ～。
No pigeons came over!
あれ？　おかしいな。
Huh? That's weird.
（男の子）ラッパじゃないと
駄目なんだよ。
It only works if it's a bugle!
トランペットだよ。
（男の子）ピアニカだもん。
You mean a trumpet!
But that's a melodica!
音楽に　国境や人種や生態は
関係ないわ。
Nationality, race, and pedigree
don't mean anything in music.
みんなで　やってみよう！
Let's all try it together!
All right!
（子供たち）やるー！
うん。
《絵になるな》
What a great picture they make.
《ブレーメンの音楽隊だ》
They're like the Bremen Town Musicians!
ハト　来た～。
Look, the pigeons came!
アハハ。
（男の子）春一番だ！
（男の子）俺の帽子～。
It's the first spring wind!
My hat!
（女の子）アハハハ…。　飛んだ～。
It flew away!
Why, you!
こらーっ！
ぎゃーっ！
You moron! Thanks to you,
I can kiss my chances for marriage goodbye!
バカ　バカ　バカ　バカ！
もう　お嫁に行けない。
I-I'm sorry! It was pure coincidence!
ご　ごめんなさい！
これは　奇跡的な偶然で！
あーっ！　私のレギンス！
おらーっ！
Hey, my leggings!
You little...
D-Don't use an instrument as a weapon!
がっ　楽器を武器にするな！
Dirty little camera creep!
You won't get away with this, you perv!
盗撮魔め！
許すまじ！　この変態！
偶然だって言ってるだろ！
What part of "coincidence" don't you understand?
俺のピアニカ…。
≪誰が　お前なんか！
Who would ever target you?
My melodica...
≪嘘ばっか！
リコーダー。
You're so full of it!
What'd you say?
My recorder...
≪何を！
≪何よ！
What'd you say?
（椿）ん～　いないなあ。
待ち合わせ場所　間違えたかな。
Hey, I don't see them.
You think they went to the wrong place?
（渡）なあ　椿
その子　ホントに　カワイイのか？
C'mon, Tsubaki.
Is this girl really that cute?
女同士のカワイイは
当てになんねーからな。
A girl calling another girl "cute"
isn't exactly credible, you know?
Ah, Kao!
あっ　かをちゃん。
Hey, Kao!
おーい　かをちゃん！
椿ちゃん！
Tsubaki!
Well, then. Let's take it from the top.
おっほん。
えー　では　あらためまして→
This is my classmate, Miyazono Kaori.
こちら　私のクラスメート
宮園かをりちゃん。
初めまして。
Nice to meet you!
And this is Watari Ryouta.
で　こいつが　渡　亮太。
こう見えても　サッカー部　部長。
He may not look it, but he's the
captain of the soccer team.
初めまして。
Nice to meet you.
She's so cute! Good job, Tsubaki!
（渡）《フフフ…　カワイイ！
椿　グッジョブ》
よろしくお願いします～。
よろしく～。
It's a real pleasure!
The pleasure's all mine!
《何たる変わり身の早さ》
（渡）カワイイね～。
How did she just pull off
such an abrupt about-face?
《見とれた自分が恥ずかしい》
I'm ashamed of myself for being so mesmerized.
Oh, and not that it really matters,
あと　どうでもいいけど
これは　友人Ａね。
but this is Friend A.
Oh!
Please excuse my earlier behavior!
先ほどは…　失礼…　しました。
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
余計なこと言ったら
殺すぞ　盗撮魔。
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
One word and you're dead, camera creep!
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
She looks like Hell incarnate...
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
地獄のような顔をして…。
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
礼儀正しい子だ～。
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
S
E
T
H
I
N
G
Wow, so polite!
やだ～　そんなことないです～。
Oh, stop! You flatter me!
（椿）ちょい　公生。
What's the big idea, Kousei?
So you're the captain of the soccer team, Watari?
先に声掛けて　抜け駆けなんて
あんたも　隅に置けないわね。
Beating him to the punch and making the first move...
Yeah, I am.
I'm pretty much the ace.
I never knew you were such a ladykiller.
The ace? So you're out on the field a lot, right?
I'm telling you, it was pure coincidence!
だから　奇跡的な偶然で。
≪渡君　すごーい！
That's amazing! You're so cool, Watari!
What are you so pissed about?
何　怒ってんの？
≪カッコイイ！
We're having a scrimmage at school.
ベー！　でも　残念でした。→
Too bad you're out of luck.
You should come cheer us on.
かをちゃんは　渡が好きなの。
Kao likes Watari.
I'll be there!
今日の　あんたは　脇役。
I'll pull a hat-trick for you
and come out with the win.
Today, you're a supporting character.
引き立て役の　友人Ａ。　諦めろ。
What's a hat-trick?
You're just Friend A, playing the foil for Watari.
When a player scores three goals
in a game, it's called a hat-trick.
Give it up!
Who'd want a vicious girl like...
誰が　あんな　凶暴女。
Huh?
あっ。　そろそろ出番だ。
すぐ　行かなくちゃ。
I'm gonna be up soon.
I've gotta get over there!
Over where?
行くって　どこに？
（椿）あそこ。
There.
あそこって…。
藤和ホール。
Isn't that...
Towa Hall.
今から　あそこで演奏するの。
I'll be performing there today.
私　バイオリニストなの。
I'm a violinist.
バイオリニスト！？　すっげー！
A violinist?
That's awesome!
Isn't it?
でしょ？
Come on, Kousei.
公生も　行こう。
僕は…　いいよ。
I... I'm gonna pass.
君も　行こっ。
Come with us.
＜１４歳の春　僕は…＞
In my fourteenth spring...
I...
Episode 1
Monotone Colorful
I'm taking off with you.
＜君と走り出す＞
Episode 2
itsumademo soba ni itai to omoeta
I realized I never want to leave your side
Friend A
Episode 2
itsumademo soba ni itai to omoeta
I realized I never want to leave your side